Eger Vaughan Murphree Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Eger Vaughan Murphree 1932-1963 (bulk 1957-1962)
MSS50146
Murphree, Eger Vaughan, 1898-1962
1,000 items
4 containers
1.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Scientist, engineer, and businessman. Correspondence, speeches, memoranda, reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, and biographical material relating primarily to Murphree's activities as president of Esso Research and Engineering Company and as an official of the Fifth World Petroleum Congress.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Lacy, William Sterling Byrd, 1910-1978--Correspondence.; McCone, John A. (John Alex), 1902-1991--Correspondence.; Murphree, Eger Vaughan, 1898-1962.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994--Correspondence.; Seaborg, Glenn Theodore, 1912- --Correspondence.; Strauss, Lewis L.--Correspondence.; Teller, Edward, 1908-2003--Correspondence.
Organizations
Esso Research and Engineering Company.; Standard Oil Company of New Jersey.; World Petroleum Congress.
Subjects
Petroleum industry and trade--Congresses.; Petroleum industry and trade.; Science--International cooperation.; Scientists--Soviet Union.
Occupations
Businessmen.; Engineers.; Scientists.
Provenance
The papers of Eger Vaughan Murphree, engineer, scientist, and businessman, were given to the Library of Congress by the Esso Research Engineering Co. in 1966.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Eger Vaughan Murphree are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1898, Nov. 3 Born, Bayonne, N.J.
1920 B.S. in chemistry, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Ky.
1921 M.S. in chemistry, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Ky. 1922-1924 Staff assistant and research associate, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass. C. Rabelais
1924 1930 Chemical engineer, chemical engineering division, Solvay Process Co., Syracuse, N.Y.; director, 1926-1930
1930 Married Madelaine Johnson (died 1933)
1930 1934 Director, Jasco Inc., Standard Oil Co.of Louisiana, development and research department
1934 Married Georgie
1934 1945 Vice president and director, Hydro Engineering and Chemical Co.
1934 1962 Manager of development and research, Standard Oil Development Co. (later Esson Research and Engineering Co.); successively, vice president, 1937-1946; executive vice president, 1946-1947; and president, 1947-1962
1941 1945 Member, Office of Scientific Research and Development
1942 1945 Member, executive committee, Manhattan Project
1950 1962 General Advisory Committee, Atomic Energy Commission
1951 1959 President, Permanent Council of the World Petroleum Congress
1956 1957 Special assistant to secretary of defense
1962, Oct. 29 Died, Overlook, N.J.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Eger Vaughan Murphree (1898-1962) span the years 1932-1963, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1957-1962. The collection consists primarily of correspondence and speeches, supplemented by reports, memoranda, newspaper clippings, photographs, and biographical information. The papers are organized into three groupings: subject file, speeches and writings, and miscellany.
The correspondence in the subject file is composed primarily of carbons or photocopies of incoming and outgoing letters for the years 1956-1962. There is no correspondence previous to 1956. The correspondence is mostly of a business nature and concerns Murphree’s activities as president of Esso Research and Engineering Company, the research and development arm of the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey, and his activities as an official of the Fifth World Petroleum Congress in the period 1956-1960. Of special interest in the Fifth World Petroleum Congress file is correspondence relating to the admission of Soviet scientists to the United States and their restriction with regard to technical information.
Correspondents include William Sterling Byrd Lacy, John A. McCone, Richard M. Nixon, Glenn Theodore Seaborg, Lewis L. Strauss, and Edward Teller.
Murphree’s writings include typed, mimeographed, and handwritten copies of his speeches, addresses, and published articles for 1932-1962. An index to the published articles is in the biographical file in the miscellany.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Subject file (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - American Chemical Society, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Chemical Engineers, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Anti-smog devices, 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Atomic energy, 1957-1962 (Box 1)
  - Atomic Industrial Forum, 1957-1962 (Box 1)
  - Chamber of Commerce, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Department of Defense activities, 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - Fifth World Petroleum Congress (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1962, (13 folders) (Box 1)
    - List of reports, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Programs, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Memoranda, 1956-1959, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fluid solids technique, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Iron ore reduction, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Letters of condolence to Mrs. Murphree, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Letters of congratulation, 1962, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1957-1962, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Non-company research activities, 1959-1962 (Box 2)
  - Permanent Council of the World Petroleum Congress, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Research activities, 1959-1962, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Sixth World Petroleum Congress, 1961-1962, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Society of Chemical Industry, 1959-1962 (Box 2)
  - Technical education, 1957-1962, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Speeches and writings (Box 3)
  - 1932-1958, (15 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1959-1962, (6 folders) (Box 4)
- Miscellany (Box 4)
  - Biographical material, including index to Murphree’s published articles (Box 4)
  - Memoranda, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Passport (Box 4)
  - Photographs (Box 4)
  - Printed matter (Box 4)
  - Report on vapor resources for the Solvay Process Co., 1936 (Box 4)